<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="example.tei.cr00002">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Anne Burrows Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 April 1872</title>
            <author xml:id="abg" ref="https://viaf.org/en/viaf/3271689">Gilchrist, Anne Burrows (1828&#8211;1885)</author>
            <editor xml:id="se">Editor, Sample</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="st">Transcriber, Sample</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Sample Institution</sponsor>
            <funder>Sample Funder</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2025</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Sample Distributor</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>1000 A Street</addrLine>
               <addrLine>A Town, State</addrLine>
            </address>
            <idno>example.tei.cr00002</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</licence>
               <p>The base text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were prepared 
                  by the editor and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons 
                     Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title level="m">Anne Burrows Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 April 1872</title>
               <author sameAs="#abg"/>
               <date cert="high" when="1872-04-12" xml:id="dat1">April 12, 1872</date>
               <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842–1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category><catDesc>correspondence</catDesc></category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName sameAs="#abg"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/en/viaf/2478331">Whitman, Walt (1819&#8211;1892)</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-01-21" who="#st">updated transcription and encoding from the Walt Whitman Archive version</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00089.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <opener>
            <address>
               <addrLine>50 Marquis Rd.</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Camden Sq. N. W.</addrLine>
            </address>
            <dateline><date when="1872-04-12">April 12<hi rend="underline">th</hi>/72.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I was to tell you about my acquaintanceship with Tennyson, which was a pleasant episode in my life at Haslemere Hearing of the extreme beauty of the scenery 
            thereabouts &amp; specially of its comparative wildness &amp; seclusion, he thought he would like to find or build a house, to escape from the obtrusive curiosity 
            of the multitudes who flock to the Isle of Wight at certain
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00092.jpg" type="verso"/>
            seasons of the year—He is even morbidly sensitive on this point &amp; will not stir beyond his own grounds from
            <choice>
               <orig>weeks</orig>
               <reg>week's</reg>
            </choice>
            end to
            <choice>
               <orig>weeks</orig>
               <reg>week's</reg>
            </choice>
            end to avoid his admiring or inquisitive persecutors—So, knowing an old friend of mine, he called on me for particulars as to the resources of the neighbourhood—And I, 
            good walker &amp; familiar with every least frequented spot of hill &amp; dale for some miles round, took him long rambles in quest of a site. Very pleasant rambles they 
            were; Tennsyon, under the influence of the fresh, outdoor quite unconstrained life in new
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00091.jpg" type="recto"/>
            scenery &amp; with a cheerful aim, shaking off the languid ennuyée air, as of a man to whom nothing has longer a relish—bodily or mental that too often hangs about him. 
            And we found something quite to his mind—a coppice of 40 acres hanging on the south side two thirds of the way up a hill some 1000
            <choice>
               <abbr>ft</abbr>
               <expan>feet</expan>
            </choice>
            high—so as to be sheltered from the cold &amp; yet have the light, dry, elastic hill air—&amp; with, of course, a glorious outlook
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00090.jpg" type="verso"/>
            over the wooded weald of Sussex so richly green &amp; fertile &amp; looking almost as boundless as the great sweep of sky over it—the South 
            Downs—the Surrey Hills &amp; near at hand the hill curving round in a fir-covered promontory, standing out very black &amp; grand between him &amp; 
            the Sun set. Underfoot too a wilderness of beauty—fox gloves (I wonder if they grow in America) ferns, purple heath &amp;c &amp;c.—I don't suppose 
            I shall see much more of him now I have left Haslemere;
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00093.jpg" type="recto"/>
            though I have had very friendly invitations; for I am a home bird—don't like staying out—wanted at home and happiest there. And I should not enjoy 
            being with them in the grand mansion half so much as I did
            <choice>
               <orig>pic-nicing</orig>
               <reg>picnicking</reg>
            </choice>
            in the road &amp; watching the builders as we did. It is pleasant to see T. with children—little girls at least—he does not take to boys—but one 
            of my girls was mostly on his knee when they were in the room &amp; he liked them very much. His two Sons are now both 6
            <choice>
               <abbr>ft.</abbr>
               <expan>feet</expan>
            </choice>
            high.—I have received your letter of March 20 from Brooklyn: but the one you speak of as having acknowledged the photograph never came
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00096.jpg" type="verso"/>
            to hand—a sore disappointment to me, dear Friend. I can ill afford to lose the long &amp; eagerly watched for pleasure of a letter. If it seems 
            to you there must needs be something unreal, illusive in a love that has grown up entirely without the basis of personal intercourse, dear Friend, 
            then you do not yourself realize your own power, nor understand the full meaning of your own words—"whoso touches this, touches
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00095.jpg" type="recto"/>
            a man"—"I have put my Soul &amp; Body into these Poems." Real effects imply real causes. Do you suppose that an ideal figure conjured up by her 
            own fancy could, in a perfectly sound healthy woman of my age; so happy in her children, so busy &amp; content, practical earnest, produce such 
            real &amp; tremendous, effect—saturating her whole life,
            <choice>
               <orig>colouring</orig>
               <reg>coloring</reg>
            </choice>
            every waking moment—filling her with such joys such such pains that the strain of them has been well nigh
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00094.jpg" type="verso"/>
            too much even for a strong frame, coming as it does, after twenty years of hard work?</p>
         <p>Therefore please dear Friend, do not "warn" me any more—it hurts so, as seeming to distrust my love—Time only can 
            show how needlessly. My love, flowing ever fresh &amp; fresh out of my heart, will go with you in all your wanderings, 
            dear Friend, enfolding you day and night soul &amp; body with tenderness that tries so vainly to utter itself in these poor 
            helpless words, that clings closer than any man's love can cling. O, I could not live if I did not believe that sooner or 
            later you will not be able to help stretching out your arms towards me &amp; saying "Come, my Darling."—When you get this 
            will you post me an American News
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_cb.00040.jpg" type="recto"/>
            paper (any one you have done with) as a token it has reached you—&amp; so on at intervals during your wanderings; it will 
            serve as a token that you are well, &amp; the post marks will tell me where you are—And thus you will feel free only to 
            write when you have leisure &amp; inclination—&amp; I shall be spared that feeling
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_cb.00041.jpg" type="verso"/>
            I have when I fancy my letters have not reached you—as if I were so hopelessly helplessly cut off from you which is more 
            than I can stand. We all read American news eagerly too.—The children are so well &amp; working with all their might. 
            The school turns out more what I desired for them than I had ventured to hope.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Good bye dearest Friend.</salute>
            <signed>Anne Gilchrist</signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>